software engineering radio episode 82
organization of large code bases with
Yodle her long
[Music]
welcome this nurse to 2008 it's the
third year of software engineering radio
to be precise the first episode was
broadcast on January 26 2006 so we have
another two episodes to go or three
until we have our official third
birthday but anyway welcome to 2008 so
if in calendar years this is the third
year before we are going to talk about
large code bases actually before ever
halt is talking to young holo about
large code bases let me again remind you
of the fact that we have this software
engineering radio get together 2008
thing on our website this is the mini
conference we're thinking about an open
space event we need to know whether
you're interested in participating
whether you want it to happen in German
or in English and all these other
organizational things so please visit
visit a Z - radio dotnet on the left
side there is a black banner basically
it shows campfire just click on it and
please reply to the bunch of questions
we have there it helps us organize the
get together and see whether it makes
sense okay so this episode is as I said
before and in a discussion between a
bahut wolf and young holla about large
code bases using the example of spring
and also you should know that a behad
and yielding both work for interface 21
or I guess they're called spring source
now so if you think this is
advertisement which I don't think but if
you think it's advertisement then well
then just stop now and listen to the
next episode otherwise have fun so you
do you want to say a few words about
yourself and the spring framework hi
everybody I'm you can holla have been
co-founder of Spring Framework project
back in early 2003 and have been
involved as lead developer and release
manager ever since the spring framework
is a well-known open source project
in the in the Java middleware web
application space it's a broad
application framework just offering
facilities for managing the internals of
an application service layer of a web
application of any kind of of internal
structure of a typical Java based
business application in most cases well
spring has the spring core so is this
what we usually refer to as the spring
framework as well as a number of sister
projects such as spring web flow spring
web services spring security and so
forth okay so obviously we are going to
talk about the specific issues of
developing frameworks
yeah and how to evolve them
one interesting thing to cover first is
how is spring actually developed I mean
it's an open source framework so you
could assume that it's done in the
distributed manner how do you do that
that's roughly how it works so we're
probably not an unusual not unusual in
that respect we open those frameworks at
least spring is largely developed by a
distributed team of course with
occasional quite regular face-to-face
meetings between members of the team we
have a quite large number of committees
more than thirty in the mean time for
spring code it is but probably pretty
pretty common like in most open-source
projects there is a smaller number of
core committees about five now in our
case we have a large number of
contributors some of them having commit
rights some of them not having commit
rights and just dropping pieces of code
in every now and then but in in the end
most of the work done on encore spring
is within the hands of very few people
really which
we need just to keep the codebase
coherent and evolving the codebase in an
organized fashion okay so obviously we
will not talk about how to organize such
teams and all the organizational issues
that come with that because spring is
not a good example for that it's more a
good example of how to evolve how to
evolve a spring a framework so why
should I even care about good
organization in the first place what is
the problem if I don't really care about
it what's what's the outcome of that um
well for a start there are quite a few
people who don't care about code
organization I would argue it's pretty
obvious if you look at a lot of the code
that's out there today even and in
particular in the open source world well
what happens if you don't care about
code organization it probably doesn't
show in the first cut of the code that
you do but over time if your codebase
grows larger and larger more
sophisticated integrated with all sorts
of third-party code bases then
management of a codebase becomes a
serious issue
the typical effect is that at some point
the codebase turns into one large chunk
of code with no clear distinction within
the code with no clear boundaries
between subsystems modules of the code
and well as you can imagine it's pretty
hard to maintain that sort of codebase
over time this can happen pretty quickly
so even if your codebase looks clean
this year just in a year's time your
codebase might even will evolve into an
unmaintainable beast the there is a
number of well-known problems in that
space I mean the most probably most
prominent being just unclear
dependencies
between packages between modules
conceptual modules of your code showing
as a circular reference within the the D
within the the overall codebase or
circular references at the large-scale
level within subsystems or even circular
references within small sub packages
within the module which still may turn
into an a maintenance nightmare over
time and so what is the actual problem
of such a circular reference the circle
of reference are the famous circular or
infamous circular reference is well a
common problem so if you look at code
base is out there a lot of them have
circular references can you give an
example well let's start with something
pretty well-known take a look at Java
dot Lang and Java dot util which of
course have been around for a while for
about 12 years and heavy both into
tightly tightly correlated piece of code
so Java language out that you tell are
of course Co evolved by the same people
but they effectively are one packaged a
they aren't separated anymore because
Java dot length depends on specific
parts of Java dot util in all sorts of
places and Java dot util of course
depends on Java dot Lang there is Java
IO involved in between so that their
problems actually bit larger than just
landed you tell but it's if you just
navigate through the JDK source code you
just find yourself jumping between Lang
and util in the IO all the time so you
you if you look at Java the length of
string which might implement some
interfaces from the IO package such as
serializable of course the io package
depends back on core on sorry the lang
package for the core language artifacts
with the java.util package they
introduced the collection framework in
Java to this essentially turned Java
util into a very central package which
all sorts of other parts
depend on including java.lang so the jdk
isn't a good example for anybody
interested in source code organization
have a look at the jdk and learn some
lessons yeah and and the point is that
in the trade okay the problem is
probably not too large because you don't
want evolve the the separate parts of
the trade okay anyway while in spring
the goal is really to have separate
modules that can each and every each and
every one of those it can be reused
independently of the other modules so
it's yeah it's not just about the
maintenance of the code that is heard by
the circles but also yeah the the reason
you reusability of those modules yes
this is arguably a problem that doesn't
really show in the JDK it shows in in
encode that small loosely coupled
sitting in higher levels of the stack
the way you just don't want your
codebase to be one big single unit of
development and deployment you want to
build independent distinct subsystems
distinct conceptual modules which just
interoperate interact at runtime and
this is what's what what's what spring
is really designed for spring is a
collection of pretty independent
subsystems which may be used
independently they are designed to be
cohesive units on their own independent
as far as possible or necessary and of
course they can be used as in framework
style just combining say the AP
framework the core container may be
transaction management in into one
single framework stack that's then how
spring is usually seen out the end world
usually Java systems are our organized
in terms of packages because that's what
the language gives out
is that also the case force for spring
is that enough or are using other
metaphors as well or other techniques
Java packages Java language packages are
certainly a core element of any kind of
source code structure source code
organization they welled up the problem
with packages is that they're just not
quite enough with standard visibilities
you may just define visibilities at the
package level so visibility within the
package or visibility to the outside
world this is a bit too well to cause
brain I mean the outside world might
fall into quite different categories in
the case of spring we have this problem
at the the SPI level mainly where some
parts of the framework just use other
parts of the framework interact with
other parts of the framework but not
necessarily we use the visible API so
this sort of of of API is what we
usually call internal API so it's of
course still an API some sister projects
external code might use those but
they're not necessarily what typical
applications use so with anything that
sits in between it's not quite the
public published API that you have out
there the poodle sometimes call a public
public API but it's not interval to the
package either other packages need to
see specific hooks and so forth this is
what the Java language or the Java
package model just as nothi so with in
spring we we do use packages of course
so we build top level packages for each
cohesive subsystem more or less there
are certain exceptions where the
packages are a bit more fine granular
but in general we've got
top level packages like such as a a o P
beans context transaction Dao web which
just indicate a distinct part of the
framework and within those packages we
then differentiate into sub packages so
we've got the central interfaces API
hooks SPI hooks common exceptions and
then specialize those parts down into
sub packages so we are we are building
on sub-packages a lot and using sub
packages in a very specific fashion
where we try to identify even even
within a subsystem within the module we
try to identify distinct
responsibilities and build specialized
code for that specialized
implementations in two distinct sub
packages which well has a number of
positive implications as may be the most
obvious one you can use those parts
independently but for our purposes it's
actually more important to be able to
navigate through the codebase to be able
to just find out which part of the code
base even in the details is responsible
for what part of the functionality so to
find yourself within the package if you
try to track down the problem or try to
add some new functionality rather than
jumping around all sorts of of packages
when you try to implement a single
specific feature so which we try to
follow that principle as far as we can
so that's quite interesting because what
you're basically saying is that the
package mechanism in Java by itself is
probably not enough instead you have to
have something like more coarse-grained
their packages in and sub packages which
is also something that other
technologies such as maven a which is a
build tool that is building up a build
modules which are obviously more
coarse-grained than just a single
package or OSGi also come up with now M
is there technology that that is
applicable in some way to spring or how
does that relate to the approach that
you are using in spring for this kind of
problems yes it is related Navin of
course is mainly a built time tool so
it's about turning your source code into
into deployment units deployment
artifacts of course this has quite
direct relationship whatever you do
within your source code
well then however you structure your
source code is going to show effect at
the distribution level in many cases you
define a conceptual module you find
conceptual boundaries you tried to
establish conceptual boundaries indicate
those boundaries within your codebase
this might turn into separate source
directories where each and every of
those subsystems sit in a separate
source directory and are probably
compiled into a separate jar file that's
not necessarily the case though so you
might also have a single source
directory maybe even just a single
around their review jar files but still
try to to design the source code to be
as loosely coupled as possible within
that single source tree so the same
mindset shows when you build deployment
units such as Java files but it's mainly
about the conceptual model that you've
got in your minds when you come up with
you the source code structure in the
first place when you evolve the source
code structure and when you just try to
navigate through the source code
structure wait no jar file or anything
else is even in the picture so it's not
just about using the right tool and and
having a tool to support you but it's
also about how to how you generally
organize your code and it have those
conceptual modules in place before you
think about which technology you are
actually using which is probably a quite
quite a good idea any
yeah so the other thing I mean we've
been talking about packages and in
modules and now if you look at your
typical sort of PowerPoint architecture
of a business system out there usually
people attempt to think in in layers is
that something that you cannot identify
or use in spring as well or a spring
somehow different because it's framework
and the pair that they are agree doesn't
apply to frameworks layering of course
is a pretty important concept in itself
but it's a bit autumnal to modules to
some degree for a framework layering is
not that central so there you may be
able to identify the his--and with in
spring there are layers of functionality
just lower layers and higher layers with
the higher layers depend on the lower
layer functionality but not the other
way around so obviously we do have that
sort of relationship but the primary
notion of code organization within the
spring code base is conceptual modules
with each module being loosely coupled
to the rest of the modules but highly
cohesive with him the module so the this
cohesion this notion of cohesion isn't
that central with layering layering
often has to do with well even
deployment where you're using the face
layer may be deployed into a separate
virtual machine service layer
application layer running in in a
server-side process so in in a typical
PowerPoint kind of diagram architecture
you'll probably identify some some
coarse-grained layers and some modules
within the layers but from the original
idea of a conceptual module layers are
secondary in my opinion the primary
notion is a module because if you have a
conceptual a concept essentially of
conceptual boundaries
this this conceptual module will evolve
will involve both some some Dao data
access related parts some process
calculation whatever related part in the
service layer maybe some some stuff in
the user interface layer it's all part
of the same concept that you introduce
into a code base and the layering is not
quite um that important then in that
respect within a typical application
architecture things are different
you usually and start with layers
although you might define modules
upfront modules are probably should be
more common even in in application
architectures but generally speaking a
framework a library is a quite separate
affair in application architecture other
factors play an important role within
the framework a library you are in a
quite different kind of world
in that respect yeah yeah speaking of
which I mean the other thing we are you
already mentioned that is that there are
those public public API switch you base
that that are used by by the users of
the framework itself and it cannot
really be changed anymore so that means
that certain of parts of the code itself
need to be stable and what so how do you
actually deal with that how do you keep
your attacker clean while still and
being able to maintain the backwards
compatibility for the public API
this is probably the biggest challenge
in in it all they this this challenge of
is well I guess more common in
frameworks and libraries than in
applications code sins within an
application you might just follow
typical HR processes where you are in
full control hopefully of the code base
and you just prefect whenever it's
necessary so if you introduce a new
concept into the CalPERS new major new
functionality you might just do some
refactoring which breaks packages you
might completely restructure your code
it doesn't matter as long as all the
colors under your control as well but in
framework in library in any kind of code
that's published to the outside world
with unknown clients or an unknown
number of clients things of course
different we within spring we need to
preserve our public public API so those
most central parts of the API that many
applications depend on in one way or the
other those need to remain stable we
need to preserve backwards company
compatibility we might be able to
introduce new functionality there new
methods in well we've got lots of
interfaces where clients typically call
into but essentially the implementations
of those interfaces all part of the
sprinkle piece are all under our control
in that case we just introduce new
methods if necessary but all present
clients will find a compatible API that
the compatible API did they expect in
other parts of the system it's a bit
more subtle if from the pure clients
perspective we establish 100% backwards
compatibility but we also have lost lots
of extension hooks lots of customization
hooks in the spring code base
and the challenge is much harder with in
in that space with those hooks since if
we introduce new internal functionality
if we do some internal restructuring to
optimize things to address new
requirements coming in we need to
refactor internals and this sometimes or
quite often actually thus affect
customization hooks extension hooks so
what do we do with people having
implemented some of those customization
hooks having done some custom sub
classes overwritten some protective
methods that's the the biggest challenge
and we try to preserve let's say a 99%
backwards compatibility even they're
using the application and so forth so we
really strive for making people's life
and not not making people's life hard
without a good reason
but in some cases it's necessary to just
really reflect a customization hook
where some new method argument comes in
some new context comes in something
changes within within the internals that
just just doesn't allow for keeping
existing customization hooks in that
space sometimes we have to decide on
that we try to do creative refactorings
preserving compatibility as far as
possible but if necessary for
introducing new functionality for
preserving architectural quality for not
compromising on architectural quality
then we change those extension hooks
customization hooks and just document it
so that people have fun people using
those hooks have a clear migration path
nevertheless so can you give an example
of such a creative refactoring well
there are quite a number of creative
refactorings that we used over time but
well quite I guess the most the most
obvious cases are in the coke container
and hippy framework where the
interaction between those depends on SPR
is that the coke
ten office and top-4 hue system and
we've we allow people to build custom
subclasses of both the core containment
classes the EOP framer classes in this
case the so called Auto proxy create a
proxy factory beam and those classes so
people do use those customization hooks
we we learned that quite a lot of people
use them just by bug reports as she
reports enhancement requests coming in
so we try to keep the established
structure there introducing new
functionality on the fly sometimes this
means introducing extended spi
interfaces concept that we came up with
over time example would be the beam post
processor for example in in spring the
auto proxy creators use a beam post
processor it's a general hook so other
implementations might implement the beam
post processor interface we had a number
of times we had to introduce new
callbacks so the auto proxy created
needed had a need for extended callbacks
so how does the co container give those
extended callbacks to the auto proxy
creator if there is an established beam
post processor comfort contract in
between and other people might rely on
it so what we are basically talking
about is a general concept the beam post
processor which allows you to have each
and every single component inside the
spring container be modified in a
certain way and the the responsibility
of the outer procs creator is to modify
a certain spring component spring beans
in a way that for example AOP stuff
aspect-oriented advisor sensor on can be
added now obviously you need to change
the auto proxy creator from time to time
and the questions how do you do that
if other people already have rely on the
same interface that is implemented by
all that can be used to modify
component which has been to being
post-processor so how do you do that
this this is what led to a number of
extended beam post-processor interfaces
so what we use is a different levels of
being post processor there's the
standard interface having just two
callback methods and for any kind of
code needing extended interfaces the the
sub interface is extended to pin post
processing interfaces he's the so-called
instantiation a way up in post processor
destruction a way up in post processor
any kind of code that needs more than a
standard pin post processor uses those
we apply different compatibility levels
to those so in general it's recommended
for any kind of client code that wants
to do custom post processing to
implement the standard pin post
processor interface which will remain
100% backwards compatible whereas in
sensational we're being post processor
might change in major versions so with
major versions jumps so it's it's one of
those ideas you can apply where you just
clearly differentiate between sort of
standard hooks with hundred-percent
compatibility guarantees and extended
hooks which might change a little over
time and your own code building on this
of course using the extended hooks
applications
hopefully mainly using the standard
hooks so basically the idea is to have
sort of the standard interface have
other interfaces inherit from those and
then use the right level of interface
for client code with public public API
and and internal code might use other
more fragile interfaces so to say more
sophisticated and more fragile powerful
yeah exactly
okay so so Spring has already evolved
quite a bit it's it started obviously in
1.0 then there were the 1.1 and one
releases and now for thing about three
quarters of here there has been spring
Tupelo out there with quite broad API so
so how did the project evolved over time
a do you do any kind of metrics about
that and and in these are those metrics
worsening or are they improving but what
is your approach in that area we do use
metrics so we do use tools approach and
we also use metrics so we try to come up
with numbers indicating certain
characteristics of the code in general
we are pretty cold centric so we we all
we just use at specific points of time
comparisons of current metrics in in
spring the the evolution from spring one
that x2 to the dough has shown that the
the internal structure of spring
actually improved so the the typical
metrics applied here he actually a
slightly better into the dough than they
we're in 1.2 this is largely because
bring the dough introduced new areas of
functionality which are pretty decoupled
on their own so even if the cold wage
grew larger the internal structure of
the code base remained clean and became
even slightly better because we allowed
we did some refactorings internally
which we were able to do for to the
dough which we didn't want to do earlier
but in in general we did preserved
roughly the same same internal quality
level indicated by those metrics so what
kind of metrics are you actually using
clients of code are what what do you do
well lines of codes is probably one of
the not-so-great metrics in this world
since the lines of code in spring
actually pretty high because we use a
lot of internal we use lots of internal
comments which
of course increase at least lines of
code in the source file what's what we
mainly use here our average component
dependencies so if you take a specific
component within a specific class for
example within the code base how many
other classes or artifacts within the
code base does this class depend on and
this is this is very very low
within spring in comparison to other
code bases because of the decoupling so
if you take any class and just look at
how this class works even from its
implementation you know there's just a
limited number of classes that you have
to go to if you just follow the
dependencies if you just open the source
file navigate down the imports it's
still a pretty reasonable small number
of classes in other code bases this is
this might be very different so other
code bases are often structured to
import well two-thirds of the rest of
the code base in one single class in
extreme cases so there are very very
different kinds of code bases out there
in that respect this is probably a good
aesthetic metric because it basically
means that changing one piece of the
code and influences just little of the
rest of the code which means that the
code base is changeable and easy
adaptable to future requirements
basically and it's also it's generally
more maintainable but indeed in
particular it's more extensible and
adaptable just because you know if you
change some specific part of the code
that this is a pretty separate distinct
crowd of the code that doesn't have an
an impact on all the rest of the code
base of course primary effect is you may
use those parts pretty independently so
you can just take a small part of the
code base and use it on its own without
having the rest of the code based on the
class path even yeah which means that
that you can use each and every feature
of the spring from more more or less
independently and probably at each and
every but large parts that the main ones
here there are also quite quite subtle
issues like for example in every project
that at least I've been to there is
usually some kind of view to a class or
even you to a package of the project's
sophisticated enough so I learned that
even though this package is subject to
the strict requirements of package
dependency in in the spring framework
and there are even it on this stuff but
there are some issues in with regards to
the dependency management yes this is
this is probably showing our general
approach at a very level level even if
you build a utility with all sorts of
functionality that well doesn't fit
anywhere else collection of static
methods stuff that really should be in
the JDK but isn't that sort of stuff
often ends up in a queue to the package
and in libraries and frameworks most
libraries have their own YouTube package
so just because they need to well to
keep their dependencies minimal there
are external depends this many more all
they do is they they include the utility
classes that they need in Springs case
we have a util package orchid spring
from kyouto which is a public package so
not only is our own code our other
packages AUP beans transaction and so
forth building on on the on on some
parts of that YouTube package it's also
available for client usage so we do
preserve backwards compatibility
client applications and extensions
third-party frameworks of party
extensions and so forth may use that
package we've also got a so called core
package octave spring from a quad core
which is also very low-level looks a bit
like a utility package but it's actually
a one small level higher so it sits on
top of you too
is allowed to depend on you to to refer
to say static methods in Utah but Utah
does not know core so it's not a way of
core and the core it of course is not
allowed to depend on artifacts in the
core package this is sometimes showing
subtle subtle effects so one problem
being that for example Springs JDK
version class and spring version classes
sit in the co-op package even Springs a
nested runtime exception sits in the
core package the resource abstraction
with class path resource file system
resource and so forth sits in the core
package so according to the the
established rule none of the that's none
of the methods none of the utility
classes in Utah is allowed to use any of
that core functionality this is
sometimes a bit hard because you might
find yourself tempted there there's that
nice abstraction in whole we could call
the GDK version check there we could use
the class path resource class we could
use nested grunt Springs own nested
runtime exception with its own nested
exception reporting well yeah you could
but you're not building in utility fast
and so the idea is util is really the
lowest level of code within the entire
code base it must not even depend on
established spring things spring isms so
it's it should be as minimal as possible
usually not even not even having a
requirement for nested exceptions
shouldn't you be doing any JDK version
checks or even spring version checks and
if it does some resource loading it
should do it as simple as possible
operating on input streams operating on
well maybe a Java IO file handles but
not using springs resource abstraction
because Teresa's abstraction sits one
level higher it uses the YouTube package
to implement a resource abstraction so
the YouTube package must not depend on
the recess abstraction itself else will
run into a circular dependency so that's
that's one example that's probably
pretty common because a lot of code
bases have a youtube package
we're we're just this this dependency
management in the details shows if you
look at code bases out there application
code bases sometimes they often got a
YouTube package but if you didn't look
at the dependencies of the total package
you find the YouTube package importing
2/3 or some of the rest of the
application because what you implement
looks like a utility method but it
depends on core concepts of other parts
of the system so it doesn't fit into the
YouTube package it's I guess part of
this is about a you tilts and in so
general and people just thinking ah what
I'm about to implement sounds like a
youtube method it doesn't matter what it
sounds like it's the only thing that
matters and that determines the place
where children happen is what does it
depend on what kind of concepts does it
really fir to that's where it has to sit
and sometimes you have to introduce more
specific util packages and that's what
we do in spring for example we have oak
that spring from cut web dot util
package we have an orchid spring firma
Kop that support package with with you
till stuff in there so we just introduce
more specific utility packages which
then implement the most specific utility
style stuff but that's a separate affair
from this low-level util package at the
very bottom of the dependency stack a
typical part of spring is the dependency
of too many thirdly third-party classes
and third-party libraries and of course
also to support different versions of
those third-party libraries so what do
you do about these I mean it basically
means that you have the same class and
you have different versions of that
class that you need to support and a
string doesn't really have versioning
system based on the classes and they
need to be some some it there are
clearly some issues associated with that
thing so what do you do about that in it
spring itself
at least in the core we fortunately
don't have many external dependencies
but in let's say the more a middleware
oriented packages subsystems within the
spring core distribution we do have and
as you pointed out those third-party
packages of the party projects products
tend to change over time so for example
we've got dedicated hibernate support
and hibernate evolves - into that one
then there's three - though but even
from three doodle onwards test3 that one
does 3.2 and there have been some
changes in the details in hibernates own
api and configuration api in particular
so what we need to do in some places to
preserve compatibility with earlier
versions of those external libraries is
just to do reflective checks so we
essentially do a runtime detection of
the concrete version that's available in
the classpath say we check whether
there's the hibernate in the habbaniyah
transaction api whether they at the set
timeout method is available there as a
concrete example which is - a reflection
based check and if it's available we are
using it if it's not available which is
well throwing an exception if we can't
implement our functionality then or just
going on with an alternative way of
achieving the same the same end this
allows us to remain compatible with
earlier versions of the libraries which
in turn allows our users to well keep
using those earlier versions if there is
somebody using hibernate 3 2005 and is
happy with it we we don't want to force
an upgrade of hibernate just because the
version of spring has been upgraded so
even from spring 1.2 1.2 - 2 - though
even in in that case we did preserve
compatibility with earlier versions to a
large degree passing so final question
of course is what do you do about the
i-th I mean we have already been talking
about
some metrics how do you actually get
them what kind of tools are using for
that we've been using various tools over
time originally we've been using J
depends just probably the simplest of
them all it's just the commands we're
using it in a command line fashion so
essentially just tell JD pen to scan
your code base and that generates a
report about the code base and within
the report you get all sorts of metrics
and in particular a package dependency
section
it just shows concretely where your
packages depend on other packages within
the system J depend isn't extremely
smart or sophisticated and it doesn't
have to be it just chose standard
metrics and standard dependency analysis
at the package level there are obvious
obvious strategies there are just a
package shouldn't depend on any other
package that in turn depends on the same
original package so JD pen doesn't have
to be configured you don't have to tell
it oh those are my modules and and so
forth you just apply it to an arbitrary
code base and get some general results
and it's free and it's free and it's
been around for a long time and it works
so we're still using J depends just to
be on the safe side
we always run different tools and see
what they what they tell us about our
code base in the meantime in the past
few years newer tools have been have
been evolving such as seongjae or
structure one-on-one tools with a GUI or
rather than just the command-line and
tools that in particular allow to be
configured for your particular code base
so you can instruct the tool you can
configure conceptual boundaries or
module boundaries between your different
modules you can associate packages with
those our conceptual modules and the
tool then performs not only package
level dependency analysis but all
so module-level dependency analysis so
those tools are significantly more
sophisticated and for basic purposes
even Jada pendous is a good start and
we're still using it as a sanity check
so to sum up obviously the evolution of
frameworks tricky especially because of
the public API is that you published and
that people out there are using and you
need to maintain backwards compatibility
for that we had some some we had this we
had some discussion about how to deal
with that and we also discussed packages
and modules in interdependencies why
they are important and also talked a
little bit about some sort routing for
that and anything you want to say to sum
up any concrete rules you want to give
the audience well I guess the gist of
the story is that a code base in
particular a larger code base is pretty
hard to evolve over time but there are
general guidelines that we learned
lessons from lessons that we learned in
the spring project that I assume can be
applied to up to similar projects and
there are some lessons learned even just
for for any kind of cope is really the
the most fundamental problem from my
perspective is just this difference of
this this contrast between backwards
compatibility requirements on the one
hand and an agile development process
process on the other hand I would
generally recommend to of course be
creative in your refactorings try to
preserve the existing structure or at
least preserve the existing structure as
an entry point even if you introduce
completely new functionality as far as
possible
if that
work out properly if you don't feel
happy with a solution the solution that
you came up with or if it just doesn't
look clean
then don't be afraid of broader
deprecation or even breaking
compatibility if necessary
it's probably just unavoidable in some
cases and as long as it's documented
probably and as long as your users and
extenders understand why you had to
introduce this change it's usually not
that big of a deal okay so thanks a lot
for this interview and thanks for
listening thanks it was my pleasure
[Music]
thanks for listening to software
engineering radio if you want to get
more information about software
engineering radio or if you want to give
us feedback please go to our website at
se - radio dot net you can also contact
the team at team at SAE - radio net
although we prefer entries in our
comment system on the website so other
people can see what you think
software engineering radio wants to
thank Henning Cowley for the intro and
outro music as well as Lipson for
providing the bandwidth this episode of
se radio as well as all other episodes
is licensed under Creative Commons
license see the soft engineering radio
website for details